本劇改編自聖經故事  將始終盡力保持《聖經》真諦
某些場景含暴力鏡頭  請觀眾自行斟酌
我見過的樂土
And I've seen the promised land.
起初  上帝創造天地
In the beginning, God created the heaven and the earth.
幸運人們的所有，都是上帝的恩賜。
而得到上帝恩賜的人就應該理所當然地為上帝行善事，
去幫助不幸的人，以此報答上帝的恩賜
For those to whom much is given, much is required.
你要愛人如己
Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.
有求必應  有問必答
Seek, and ye shall find. Ask, and it shall be given.
神的旨意是在天堂，上帝成全我
As the will of God is in heaven, even so let it be.
上帝是我們的避難所和力量
God is our refuge and strength.
這是史上最強大的故事
The most powerful story of all time...
至今仍在繼續塑造我們的世界
continues to shape our world.
這是我們政府的基礎
It's the foundation of our governments,
我們的法律的藍圖
the blueprint for our laws,
在人生旅程的一個神聖的指南
a sacred guide for life's journey.
歡迎收看《聖經故事》
This is the Bible.
《聖經故事》
第一季  第01集
上帝警告我  要我造一艘船
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
上帝同我說話了
God has spoken to me.
他將指引我們去新的家園
He will lead us to a new home.
他保證我的後裔會多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
你是誰   我是摩西
- Who are you? - My name is Moses.
上帝派我回來的  給你們自由
God has sent me to set you free.
耶和華帶我們離開了埃及   他承諾將賜予我們這塊土地
The Lord brought us out from Egypt, promised us this land.
很快它將屬於我們
Soon it will be ours!
耶路撒冷  我們的新家園
Jerusalem. Our new home.
大衛，你造就了地球上的神的國家
David, you have forged God's nation on Earth.
國家和民族在萬能的造物主下
A nation and a people find faith...
找到了信仰
in an all-powerful Creator.
上帝與我同在
God is with me!
他們的故事幫助我們認清自己
Their story helps define who we are...
做出選擇   如何生活
The choices we make, how we live,
如何愛
how we love,
如何奮斗和克服
how we struggle and overcome.
是誰創造了大地  大海  天空？
Who created the earth, the sea, the sky?
是誰創造了你們
Who created you?
主啊！
Lord!
給我們這座城市的主
We give this city to the Lord!
耶利哥是我們的！
Jericho is ours!
凡是離開耶路撒冷   請自便
Whatever's left of Jerusalem, help yourselves.
這是給我們所有人的陷阱  他們想要我們死
It's a trap for all of us. They want us dead.
上帝是從巴比倫帶來的災難
God is bringing disaster from Babylon!
女士，我相信你的兒子就是他的人民選擇的國王
Lady, I believe your son is the promised king of his people.
他叫什麼名字
What is his name?
耶穌
Jesus.
他的名字叫耶穌
His name is Jesus.
你說有麻煩了
You said there was trouble.
人們紛紛涌向約翰這個野人   他們認為他是一個先知
The people are ?ocking to this wild man, John. They think he's a prophet.
有些人甚至稱他為彌賽亞
Some even call him the messiah.
有一個人來施火洗禮
There is one to come who will baptise with fire.
我只是一個在荒野中的聲音
I am just a voice in the wilderness, preparing the way for the...
主啊,我們該做些什麼
Lord, what are we going to do?
改變世界
Change the world.
瑪麗 ！他在這裡!
Mary! He's here!
誰？  耶穌
Who? Jesus!
他終於又回來了
He's back at last!
貧窮的人有福了   因為天國是他們的
Blessed are the poor, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
溫柔的人有福了  因為他們必承受地土
Blessed are the meek, for they shall inherit the earth.
你在說什麼，你是彌賽亞，上帝派來的
What are you saying- that you are the messiah, the chosen one sent by God?
開始了
It has begun.
如果你們渴望正義  跟隨我  你們必將達成所願
Your hunger for righteousness, it will be filled through me.
5000年來見他   5000年
5,000 came to see him. 5,000.
你的王騎著驢來到你這裡
Your king comes to you riding on a donkey.
有一些不尋常的東西給他
There is something unusual about' him.
沒有什麼不尋常的地方，除了他有能力造成嚴重破壞
There is nothing unusual about him apart from his ability to cause havoc.
如果騷亂今天重復發生
If the disturbances that took place today are repeated,
我將粉碎任何反抗
I will crush any rebellion.
起初
In the beginning,
上帝創造天地
God created the heavens and the earth.
上帝說
And God said,
要有光
「Let there be light!」
於是就有了光
And there was light.
然後上帝分離水和天空
Then God separated the water and the sky.
造就了海洋
He formed the seas...
和土地
and the land.
然後他覆蓋了陸地
Then he covered the land...
地上長出各類樹木
with trees...
和植物
and plants.
然後他傳遍世界
Then he filled the world...
水中有了各類生物
with all the creatures of the sea...
空中有了各種飛鳥
Of the air...
地上有了各種動物
And all the creatures of the ground.
然後
And then...
上帝創造了我們
he made us...
住在伊甸園中
to live in paradise,
直到  亞當和夏娃違背了上帝的旨意
until Adam and Eve disobeyed God...
偷食了禁果
and ate the forbidden fruit.
這個選擇
And with one choice...
讓他們辨識了
they learned both good...
善與惡
and evil.
從那之後  因為該隱殺了亞伯
Since then, since Cain killed Abel,
上帝目睹了人類內心深處太多的惡念
God has seen too much evil in human heads.
錯誤的選擇  錯誤的決定
Wrong choices. Wrong decisions.
導致了今天的這一切
That's why this is happening
我們的造物主決定凈化這片土地
Our Creator decided to cleanse the earth.
上帝警告我  要我造一艘船
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
一艘能拯救我的家人和所有動物的船
A boat to save our family and all the animals.
而其他所有的生物
Every other living creature...
都將死亡
would die.
第七日
And on the seventh day,
上帝   歇息了
God... rested.
洪水吞過世界後
After the ?ood waters engulfed the world,
諾亞後裔有了全新的開始
the Bible describes a new beginning for Noah's descendants...
這也是一個人類與上帝
and a chance to restore the relationship...
重修舊好的契機
Between God and humanity.
全能的造物主13天誕生了一個新的信仰
A new faith in an all-powerful Creator 13 being born.
在無數人信仰上帝前
But before billions can believe in him,
必定要有一人聽到他的召喚
one man must hear God's voice...
並願意從此追隨他
and have the faith to follow.
亞伯拉罕  離開你的家鄉
Abraham, leave your home...
我將賜予你和你的後裔新地  去那裡吧
and go to the land I will give to you and your offspring.
我會祝福你
I will bless you.
我會讓你成為萬國的父
I will make you a father of many nations,
你的後裔將多如繁星
with descendants as numerous as the stars.
地上所有的民族
All the peoples on earth...
皆因你得福
will be blessed through you.
等等我
Wait for me!
撒拉   上帝同我說話了
Sarah, God has spoken to me.
跟我來
Come with me.
我的侄兒  羅得  跟我走
Lot, my nephew, walk with us.
亞伯拉罕
Abraham?
他將指引我們去新的家園
He will lead us to a new home.
但我們已經有一個很好的家了
But... we have a home, a good home.
遠離城鎮  去一片新的陸地上
Away from the city to a new land...
為了我們的孩子
for our children.
但你沒有孩子  也永遠不會有
But you have no children. You can never have children.
我們會有的
But we will.
他保證我的後裔會多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
他同我說話了  他向我承諾的
He spoke to me. He promised.
撒拉  相信我
Sarah, believe me.
相信我
Believe me.
羅得
And, Lot,
你和我一起去嗎
you are with me?
他會指引我們去一片神奇之地
He will lead us to a land of wonder.
不行
No.
不要
真是神跡
Such wonder!
亞伯拉罕深信  他將成為一個大國之父
Driven by the belief that he will father a great nation,
他帶領自己的小部落前往上帝與他立約的新地
Abraham leads his small tribe to the land promised to him by God.
我還能做什麼  別的土地都被占領了
What else can I do? All the other land is taken.
你不能搶我的
No! You can't have mine!
快  快
Now! Now!
住手  走開
Stop! Come away!
不能再這樣下去了   你得告訴亞伯拉罕我們的決定
This can't go on. You've got to tell Abraham what we decided.
怎麼了
What's going on?
他的人想霸占我們的草地
His men are trying to take our pasture.
上帝讓我們共享這片地
God gave us this land to share.
那他應該再多給一些
Then he should have given us more of it.
告訴他
Tell him.
亞伯拉罕  土地不夠   我們人太多了
Abraham, there just isn't enough land. There are too many of us.
耶和華會給我們的  要有信心
The Lord will provide. Have faith.
相信看不見的上帝嗎
In a god we cannot see?
是時候分道揚鑣了
It's time we go our separate ways.
不  我們必須團結在一起
No. No, we must stay together.
待在一起餓死嗎
Stay and starve?
待在一起  眼看大家因一片草葉而自相殘殺嗎
Stay and watch our men kill each other over a blade of grass?
叔叔
Uncle,
我們打算離開
we're leaving.
那好吧
Very well.
你們想去哪裡
Where do you want to go?
所多瑪附近有更茂盛的草地
To the greener pastures closer to Sodom.
所多瑪
Sodom?
保重
Take care.
亞伯拉罕沒有自己的孩子
With no children of his own,
侄子羅得對他來說  就如同兒子一般
Abraham's nephew Lot is the closest thing he has to a son.
如果我連自己的家人都領導不了
How can I lead a people...
又如何去領導一個民族呢
when I can't even lead my own family?
快  幫幫他
Quickly! Help him!
是羅得的人  這是雷米爾
It's one of Lot's men! It's Lemuel.
快   有人幫他
Hurry! Somebody help him!
來  靠在我身上
Here. Lean on me.
發生了什麼事   我們毫無勝算
What happened? We didn't stand a chance.
他們人太多了
There were so many of them.
羅得呢   還活著
And Lot? Alive.
但被抓走了   幫他一把
- But taken prisoner. - Help him.
扶著我的手  靠在我身上
Here. Take my hand. Lean on me.
這樣好受點
That's better.
好好照顧他
Tend to him.
我們有些精練的壯丁
We have some trained men.
亞伯拉罕  你們不是士兵
Abraham, you are not soldiers.
是我告訴他們要相信上帝  是我讓羅得跟我們一起來的  但後來他們離開了
I told them to trust in God. I made Lot come with us. And then they left us.
他們選擇了想要生活的地方   那是他們的決定   他們是我的家人
They had their pick of the land. It was their choice. They are family.
我們必須幫他們
We have to help them.
上帝會眷顧我們的
God will take care of us.
我看這個得有人幫忙制住她
What about this one, eh?
別碰她
Leave her alone there!
放開她
Let her go!
別碰她
Leave her alone!
相信上帝
Trust in God!
你沒事吧
Are you all right?
羅得
Lot.
Oh, Lot.
以寡敵眾
So few of us against so many.
上帝的確與我們同在
God is with us.
亞伯拉罕
Abraham.
我們還是要去所多瑪
We're carrying on to Sodom.
羅得  我們必須團結在一起
Lot, we must stay together.
不
No.
不  叔叔
No, Uncle.
我們不能回去
We can't.
城裡才有未來
We have to carry on.
我們走
Let's go.
亞伯拉罕
Abraham.
進來吧
Come inside.
這麼多星星
The stars.
-亞伯拉罕  -星星
Abraham? The stars.
滿天的星星
All of them.
來數一數   亞伯拉罕
Count them. Abraham.
來數數  數數
Count them. Count them.
我們的造物主  噓
Our Creator- Shh.
他創造了星星
Who made the stars,
也會賜給我們無數後裔
will give us as many descendants...
噓   噓   噓
Shh, Shh, Shh.
世代居住在自己的土地上
To populate our land.
他答應過
He has promised.
你會有孩子的   我不會有
You will have a child. I won't.
你會的   不會
You Will! I won't!
我不能
I can't.
我的年紀太大了
It's too late for me.
但你還是有機會的
For you, there's still a chance.
她
Her.
夏甲   那個女仆
Hagar, the servant girl.
不
No.
不  不行
No, no, no.
不可以
No.
可以的
Yes.
拿穩了  以實瑪利
Hold it steady, Ishmael.
撒拉  你看到沒
Sarah, did you see that?
看到沒   我的好兒子
Did you see that? Oh, my boy!
我的好兒子
My boy!
「My boy.」
是你的好兒子
Your boy.
跟你媽媽去吧
Go with your mother.
亞伯拉罕
Abraham.
歡迎  我主
Welcome, Lord.
請進來說話吧
Please join me.
端水過來  為客人備好食物
Bring water. Prepare food for our visitors.
是  主人
Yes, master.
你們是遠道而來嗎
Have you travelled far?
是的
Yes.
漫漫長路
A long WHY...
亞伯拉罕  你的妻子在哪兒
Abraham, where is your wife?
在那裡面
In there.
明年  撒拉會生下一個男孩
Next year, Sarah will have a son.
你為什麼笑
Why do you laugh?
-我沒有笑  -你笑了
But I did not laugh. You did.
誕下孩子之後
And when you have a son,
要給他起名叫做以撒
you will name him Isaac,
意為笑聲
which means 「laughter.」
感謝你的熱情款待
Thank you for your hospitality.
我們得走了
We must go.
路上需要我幫忙嗎
Can I help you on your way?
你們要去哪裡
Where are you going?
去決定所多瑪的命運
To decide the fate of Sodom.
滾開
Get out of here!
所多瑪變得墮落
Sodom has become corrupt,
成了罪惡之城
a city of sin.
但我的侄子羅得生活在那
But my nephew Lot lives there.
他們全家都在那
He has a family.
世人對所多瑪非常不滿
The outcry against Sodom is great'.
那裡罪孽深重
Its sins are very grave.
你們要毀滅它嗎
You're going to destroy it.
整座城市
The whole city?
你是公平的上帝
You are a just God.
殲滅惡人的同時
Will you destroy the good men...
-這邊  -也要消滅那些好人嗎
- Inside. ...along with the evil ones?
拜托  救命
Please! Help!
救救我們
Help us!
救命
Help!
假若所多瑪城裡有五十個義人呢
What if there were 50 good people in Sodom?
他們要和那些惡人承受同樣的命運嗎
Will they suffer the same fate as the wicked?
請救救我們
Please help us!
我們會考驗他們
We will test them.
若是我的天使能在所多瑪找到五十個正直的人
If my angels find 50 righteous people in Sodom,
我會赦免整座城市
I will spare the whole city.
求求你  幫幫我們
Please. Help us.
-他們往這邊跑了  -救救我們
They went this way! Help us.
假若只有三十個呢  二十個
Or fewer. Thirty. Twenty.
你不會毀滅他們的  是嗎
You would not destroy them, surely.
-求你了  -在那邊
Please. There! Down there!
救救我們
Help us!
拜托   這邊
Please. This way.
如果所多瑪裡只有十個義人又如何呢
What if there were 10 righteous men in Sodom?
您會對他們見死不救嗎
Would you not save them?
羅得  你在幹嘛  他們是什麼人
Lot, what are you doing? Who are these people?
他們需要我們的幫助
They need our help.
我會盡力而為
I'll do what I can for you.
即使只有十個
Even if I find only 10,
我也會赦免整座城市
I will save the whole city.
-這邊  -他們可以在哪裡
This way! Where can they be?
-給我出來   出來
- Show yourselves! - Show yourself!
母親
Mother.
噓
Shh!
那是什麼
What's that?
他們在門後面   在那邊
They're behind the door! Over there!
開門  開門   他們想要什麼
- Open the door! Open the door! - What do they want?
羅得   把陌生人交出來
- Lot! - Give us the strangers!
把他們交出來
Bring them out!
他們是我的客人   讓我們過去
They are guests in my house. Let us pass!
別再糾纏不休了   我們要把你一起抓起來
Let them be! Or we'll take you too!
給我出來
Show yourselves!
Send them out!
讓開
Step aside.
-我們必須馬上離開  -我看不見了
- We must go. - I can't see!
快點
Come on!
托亞伯拉罕的福  耶和華在救你們
For Abraham's sake, the Lord is saving you.
繼續跑
Keep moving. That's it.
等等
Wait.
他們在那兒
There they are!
我們走
Let's go.
亞伯拉罕  要永存信念
Have faith, Abraham.
你們現在安全了
You are safe now.
你們必須離開  這座城市即將受到懲罰
You must get away. The city is being punished.
繼續跑   快點
Keep moving. Come on!
繼續跑   繼續跑   快點
Keep moving. Keep moving. Come on.
不可回望這座罪孽之城
Do not look back at the city of sin!
相信上帝
Believe in God.
不要回頭
Do not look back!
羅得
Lot.
快點
Come on!
不要回頭
Don't look back!
不要
No!
羅得之妻因違背上帝之意
Lot's wife is turned into a pillar of salt...
化為了一根鹽柱
for disobeying God.
羅得和他的女兒逃到山上
Lot and his daughters ?ee to the mountains,
從此再也無法見到亞伯拉罕
never to see Abraham again.
她怎麼樣了
How is she?
哦   哦
Oh. Oh.
哦
Oh!
是個男孩
A boy.
以撒
Isaac.
如他所應許的
As he promised.
哦
Ooh!
你們的面包
Your bread.
吃吧  以實瑪利
Eat your food, Ishmael.
以實瑪利
Ishmael.
這邊   快
This way! Come on!
我來了   快點   快點
- I am! ' Hurry! Hurry!
啊
Ah.
做得不錯
Oh, good.
撒拉
Sarah?
怎麼了
What's the matter?
那個女人以為她的兒子會承受屬於以撒的一切
That woman thinks her boy is going to inherit what rightfully belongs to Isaac.
這是什麼意思
What do you mean?
亞伯拉罕  我們一族的領導人會是誰
Who is to be the first of all our tribe, Abraham...
天上引領眾星的星星又會是哪一顆
the first star of all those stars in the heavens?
是我們的兒子
Our son...
還是她的兒子
or hers?
撒拉  我... -亞伯拉罕
Sarah, I- Abraham.
亞伯拉罕
Abraham!
你決定
You decide!
媽媽
Mama.
或者讓上帝來決定
Or let God decide.
勇敢一點
Be brave.
上帝向他保證  夏甲和以實瑪利會活下來
Assured by God that they will survive,
於是亞伯拉罕將他們送去了荒野
Abraham sends Hagar and Ishmael into the wilderness.
再見了  以實瑪利
Good-bye, Ishmael.
我的孩子
Oh, my boy.
My boy.
待你長大之後
When you grow up,
上帝會賜予你眾多子嗣
God will bless you with many children.
嗯
Mmm.
我去給你做點早點  以撒
Let me make you some breakfast, Isaac.
歷經困苦歲月
After years of struggle,
亞伯拉罕明白了被上帝選中既是恩賜
Abraham has learned that to be chosen by God...
也是考驗
is a blessing and a test.
他必須證明他的忠誠
He must prove his faith...
一次又一次
again and again.
祭祀
A sacrifice.
不
No.
你還不相信我的忠誠嗎
Have I not shown you enough faith?
以撒
Isaac.
多吃點
Eat up.
等你有了自己的孩子   你就會想讓他們長得高高壯壯...
When you have children of your own, you'll want them to grow up as big and...
亞伯拉罕
Abraham?
怎麼了
What's the matter?
上帝想要一個祭品
God wants a sacrifice.
我的孩子   跟我來
My boy, come with me.
你好
Hello.
父親  柴火是有了
Father, we have the firewood.
但是羊羔呢
But where's the lamb?
耶和華會准備好祭品的  孩子
The Lord will provide a sacrifice, my son.
亞伯拉罕來問你要羊羔了嗎
Did Abraham take a lamb?
沒有  夫人
No, mistress.
把柴火拿來
Bring the wood.
父親
Father?
你要做什麼
What are you doing?
父親  你弄疼我了
You're hurting me, Father.
以撒   你一定要相信上帝
Isaac, we must trust in God.
不  求您了
No. Please.
不
No.
求您了
Please.
求求您了  父親
Please, Father.
原諒我
Forgive me.
求求您了
Please.
亞伯拉罕
Abraham!
祭品
A sacrifice.
孩子  我的孩子   我的孩子
On, my boy, my boy, my boy...
不  不
No. No.
以撒
Isaac!
媽媽
Mother!
亞伯拉罕通過了最後的考驗
Abraham has passed the ultimate test.
他將成為萬國之父
He will become the father of God's nation.
接下來就到以撒了
Now it's up to Isaac.
他會有一個叫雅各的孩子
He will have a son called Jacob.
上帝會為他重新起名叫以色列
God will rename him Israel.
上帝曾對他許諾的後裔如繁星般眾多
The promise of descendants as numerous as the stars...
漸漸成真了
is coming true.
但不久後  飢荒迫使以色列人遠離應許之地
But famine forces the Israelites far from the promised land...
來到埃及
to Egypt...
在那裡  他們成為了法老的奴隸
Here they are enslaved by Pharaoh.
亞伯拉罕和上帝成了遙遠的記憶
Abraham and God become a distant memory,
他的子民都淪為役畜
all his people reduced to beasts of burden,
只有一人幸免於難
except one.
摩西
Moses.
下集《聖經故事》預告
Next time on The Bible.
你不能再去爭強斗勇了  我無法拒絕
- You're not going to fight again. - I can't refuse.
他是法老的兒子
He's Pharaohs son.
還手  我命令你
Fight me! I order you!
Yaah!
你根本非我族人   他在說什麼
- You're not one of us. - What's he talking about?
你是奴隸之子
You were born a slave.
你的人民就在外面  摩西   不  唉
- Your people are out there, Moses. - No! Aaah!
那些以色列人   快跑
- The Israelites. - Run!
新生活歡迎你  摩西
Welcome to your new life, Moses!
你現在什麼都不是了
You are nothing now!
你是亞伯拉罕的神
You are the God of Abraham.
我會做到   我會讓我的人民獲得自由
I will do it. I will set my people free.
仍舊水深火熱
So much suffering.
求求您了
Please!
你是誰   我叫摩西
- Who are you? - My name is Moses,
約書亞
Joshua.
上帝派我回來給你們自由
God has sent me to set you ?ee.
你到這兒來做什麼  摩西   讓我的子民離開
- Why are you here, Moses? - Let my people go.
自由了   他們可以自由選擇
Freedom? They are free to choose.
奴役或死亡
Slavery or death!
我這一生都被法老奴役   我再也不會是個奴隸了
All my life I have been Pharaohs. I will never be a slave again.
約書亞  上帝與我們同在
Joshua, God is with us.
死亡天使會降臨
The Angel of Death is coming.
滾   帶著你們那卑鄙的上帝滾出我的國土
Go! And leave my land!
滾出我的國土
And take your wretched God with you!
埃及人追來了   他們追來了
The Egyptians-they're here.
耶和華
Lord!
跟我走
Follow me!
給我活捉摩西
Bring me Moses!